<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aphonologos. A dumb speech. Or, A sermon made, but no sermon preached, at the funerall of the right vertuous Mrs Mary Overman, wife to Mr Thomas Overman the younger. Of the parish, formerly called, Saint Saviours, or vulgarly Mary Overis, in Southwarke. By B. Spencer, minister of Bromley.</title>
            <author>Spencer, Benjamin, b. 1595?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1180_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason C.54.aa.1(3)</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208123</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867113</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119403</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119403)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 167:E1180[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aphonologos. A dumb speech. Or, A sermon made, but no sermon preached, at the funerall of the right vertuous Mrs Mary Overman, wife to Mr Thomas Overman the younger. Of the parish, formerly called, Saint Saviours, or vulgarly Mary Overis, in Southwarke. By B. Spencer, minister of Bromley.</title>
                  <author>Spencer, Benjamin, b. 1595?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Clark, and are to be sold at his shop under Saint Peters Church in Corn-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title is in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears in catalogue and on film as C.54.aa.1(3).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Overman, Mary --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>'ΑΦΩΝΟ'ΛΟΓΟΣ. A DVMB SPEECH. OR, A SERMON made, but no Sermon preached, at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Right Vertuous, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> MARY OVERMAN, <hi>Wife to</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> THOMAS OVERMAN, the younger. Of the Pariſh, formerly called, Saint <hi>Saviours,</hi> or vulgarly <hi>Mary Overis,</hi> in <hi>Southwarke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>B. Spencer,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Bromley.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reaſon you may find, if you reade the Epiſtle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>If theſe ſhould hold their peace, the ſtones would cry.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>S. Gregor. Moral.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Humilitas aperit, Superbia ſcientiam operit.</hi>
                     </p> 
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for JOHN CLARK, and are to be ſold at his ſhop under Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Corn-hill.</hi> 1646.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:2"/>
                  <head>To the worthily reſpected, and his much honoured friend, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> THOMAS OVERMAN: <hi>B. S.</hi> wiſheth all happineſſe.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHen God made Man, he left nothing to make more but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Man, that Man might eternally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy himſelfe. For he fore-ſeeing that Man would loſe himſelfe, though he had made him perfect, ſo farre as was conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with ſuch a creature, determined to finde him againe, by ſearching him out through bryars, and brakes, and buſhes, worſe then thoſe Thickets in Paradiſe, in which Man hid himſelfe after he had ſinned. In theſe thornes Chriſt was caught, like <hi>Abrahams</hi> Ramme, by the head, whoſe ſeed whilſt he took hold of, he was taken hold of, and by wicked hands crucified and ſlaine, for bearing witneſſe to the truth. If the Sonne of God, the
<pb facs="tcp:119403:3"/>Lord of glory hath thus ſuffered for the Servants, ſhall not the ſervants for their Lord and Maſter? All this he did to ſet us an example, to take up the croſſe, whoſe heavie burthen the world will impoſe upon his diſciples ſufficiently, though the world like the Phariſee, will not touch it, nor endure the touch of it with one finger.</p>
                  <p>Let the world ſtraine at Gnats, and ſwallow Camels; I am perſwaded better things of you, and your worthy family, though I thus ſpeak. For as you have been ever induſtrious to finde the truth, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting to ſupport it, in what ſhape ſoever it hath appeared to you, being not aſhamed of the Croſſe of Chriſt. Now as you have not been aſhamed of it, ſo you muſt not be dejected under it. Though, I confeſſe, the loſſe of ſo vertuous a wife, is a great tryall; But to be prevented of her due obſequies, addeth to the affliction; being a cuſtome allowed by all Nations to the dead, except by the <hi>Maſſagetae</hi> of <hi>Scythia,</hi> who eate up their anceſtors to prevent the wormes; and the <hi>Hircanians</hi> and <hi>Caſpians,</hi> who buryed the dead in the mawes of wild beaſts, and the gorges of vultures, to prevent Funerall charges (peradventure.) As the <hi>Bactrians</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb facs="tcp:119403:3"/>their dead by dogs, kept for that purpoſe, to avoid all Funerall ceremonies. Which buryalls were good enough for them, who neither feared God, nor reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced Man, who made no difference of a dead man, and a meere Carrion, as ſome doe not of a dead Chriſtian, who dies in hope, and an Heathen that dies without. Whoſe ſtupidneſſe neither the examples of Scripture, nor Antiquity, nor laudable Cuſtomes, nor the allowance of the State, nor the permiſſion of the Reverend Synod, can remove. Poore ſoules! What Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie now troubles them, being the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie (by them ſo called) is taken away?</p>
                  <p>But this prevention of your Funerall Rites, happened through your love to me, and your earneſt deſire, that I ſhould doe that laſt duty for your deare Spouſeſſe. Which prevention I feared, and premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, though you had the leave of all thoſe that were intereſſed in the Church. For thoſe few that in your parts diſaffect me, are of <hi>Ammons</hi> diſpoſition, (it ſeems) who when he had raviſhed <hi>Thamar,</hi> could not abide the ſight of her, though he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had done the wrong. Like an Ape, he would break that glaſſe, which ſhewed him his viſage. God forgive the, they
<pb facs="tcp:119403:4"/>have raviſhed me of my living by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtructions where I lived many yeares in good repute (I thanke God) taking great paines as is well knowne, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no juſt offence; what ever ſome might take through ignorance or ill will, (which never ſpeaketh well) though now ſome cannot abide to ſee me, becauſe they ſee their owne ill deeds in me. Which it ſeems <hi>facient iterùm, ſi ſe feciſſe crediderint,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Seneca;</hi> hoping to over-awe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice by their violence, and to make Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, like themſelves, take pleaſure in oppreſſion.</p>
                  <p>But their troubling of me turned to my good, for the Honorable Committee found themſelves abuſed, by their falſe reports, as well as my ſelfe. Now therefore, being I was prevented of preaching this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, by their falſe ſuggeſtions, procuring a Warrant, which took me off as I went before the Corpſe, I cannot deny your juſt requeſt for a Copy of that, which I meant to have ſaid at that time. Wherein you may and ſhall perceive, how fearfull theſe men were, where no feare was.</p>
                  <p>For the falſe accuſation of our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to preach, without the Miniſters conſent, and the rumour of Souldiers rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:119403:4"/>to ſupport me, and Malignants gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together to heare me, was but a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous pretence to get a Warrant to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sermon, The thing therefore which they feared, was no carnall wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, but the Spirituall weapons of the true Chriſtian warfare, <hi>viz:</hi> the ſword of the Spirit the word of God, with two edges, and the mutiny which that might make in their own guiltie conſciences, of which you will finde me very tender in this Sermon: (not that I would excuſe ſinne, but) becauſe I would take occaſion, from them that ſeek occaſion, to blame my Miniſtery of ſpleene or partiality.</p>
                  <p>As therefore you have the greateſt part in the Croſſe, and the greateſt right to the Sermon, ſo I pray accept it as a crouch to reſt the Croſſe upon. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that the devill bid Chriſt caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe downe; worldly ſorrow ſeconds him; I hope you are too wiſe with Chriſt, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey either; much leſſe to vexe your ſelfe at thoſe, who doe after evill counſell.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.1.</note> The fooles ſport is to do miſchief, for he flings fire-brands, and ſaith it is in jeſt. Let them therefore walk in the light of their owne fire,<note place="margin">Iſa. 50.11.</note> and in the ſparks that they have kindled, they ſhall at laſt ſit downe in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.
<pb facs="tcp:119403:5"/>For the deceitfull man ſeldome roſteth what he took in hunting. <hi>Non gaudet tertius haeres.</hi> But as the crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thornes under a pot, ſo is a fooles joy, ſoone in, and as ſoone out. God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the way of the righteous, but the way of the ungodly ſhall periſh.</p>
                  <p>I meane not hereby that you ſhould ſo carry this wrong, as to be infenſible of it. For <hi>Ferendo injuriam, fortaſſe invitas novam:</hi> A wrong not rightly carryed, may invite another: But ſo to beare your ſelfe, that <hi>Dum non vis calcari, neque videaris poſſe calcari,</hi> as you would not be trodon, ſo to ſhew your ſelf above their wretched ſpleene, by whoſe teeth a poore wretched corps cannot paſſe without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſnapt at. But as it was ſaid of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> ſo let it be of you, who retreating in the reare of his retyring Troops, lookt with ſuch a countenance, as put courage in his purſued friends, and daunted his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing enemies. Even as a friend of yours, a Commander, did look that day upon the guilty faces of your Funerall-diſturbers, whom they anſwered with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king faces, <hi>altero ad frontem ſublato, altero ad mentum depreſſo ſupercilio,</hi> by pulling one eye-brow up, and the other
<pb facs="tcp:119403:5"/>down, or elſe turning their backs. God keep every good man from envy, hatred, malice, and uncharitable men.</p>
                  <p>So entreating I may be excuſed for ſo long detaining your right from you, which you had received long ſince in a better character, but that mine adverſaries ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts, have bred upon me <hi>Calculum in renibus,</hi> the Stone in the Kidneys; a diſeaſe I never knew till I fell into the gravell-pits of their digging, where I have ſuffered by paine and griefe a petty martyrdome.</p>
                  <p>But God, I hope, who hath, will ſtill deliver me from unreaſonable men, and from every evill way. To whom I commit you, and all your worthy family, reſting</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your devoted ſervant in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Benjamin Spencer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:6"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>WHoſoever reades this Copy, I ſuppoſe will find nothing in it worth ſo much adoe, as Envy made to prevent the preaching of it. But as Envy is a <hi>Monoculus,</hi> ſo alſo, ſhe is ſuſpicious. She had but one eye, and that is a bad one, but many jealouſies of thoſe ſhe lookes aſquint upon. Doe not thou looke throw her ſpectacles, and thou wilt find in the Author, rather worke for pitty, then Envy, and his Sermon rather craving mercy, then deſerving malice. Read then whithout prejudice, this dumb Sermon of his, whom his adverſaries account no better of, then a dead dog. Thou needſt not think the worſe of him,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.13.</note> nor it. The Apoſtles were recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the filth and off-ſcouring of all things. And Turks call Chriſtians dogs. And I wonder not when brethren of the ſame Family are falne out, to hear them
<pb facs="tcp:119403:6"/>miſcall one another. For from among our ſelves muſt men ariſe, ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things, ſaith S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Well,<note place="margin">Acts 20.30.</note> let them ſpeak, doe thou read. It may be <hi>Mutimagiſtri,</hi> dumb teachers, ſuch as Books are, may give thee more light then ſome great talkers. God direct thee, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>Pag. 6. lin. 27. r. <hi>Cerinthus.</hi> p. 15. l. 17. r. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtris.</hi> p. 22. l. 18. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 31. l. 26. r. <hi>vagula, blandula.</hi> ibid. l. 27. r. <hi>wandring ſporting ſoule.</hi> p. 42. l. 23. r. <hi>diſpoſall.</hi> p. 45. l. 22. r. <hi>the Living.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:7"/>
                  <head>An Introduction to the Sermon.</head>
                  <p>THe Directory,<note place="margin">His ſpeech intended before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Text.</note> ſet forth by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent Synod, gives Miniſters leave at Funeralls, to put the living in remembrance of their dutie. And I will doe no more. And I hope that will give no offence to any good Chriſtian; ſince that, is not, to ſtrow complementall flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers upon the hearſe of the dead, but will rather prove ſupplementall ornaments to the living. I therefore being partly acquainted with our deceaſed Siſters life, and death, and requeſted therefore to this office by her friends, who ſeing her lamp, went not out in darkneſſe, was loth that her earthen veſſell ſhould be interred without ſome light, which might direct others, how to walk from the womb, to the tomb. Leave therefore being firſt obtained of your Miniſter, and Officers of this Church, I have thought good to preſent you, as a ſubject of your contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation with ſuch a peice of ſcripture, as may both anſwer to our dead Siſter, the patterne, and to us, the living portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. Which you ſhall find delineated by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Philip. 1.21.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119403:7"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PHILIP. 1.21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>For to me to live is Chriſt, and to die is gaine.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ISE <hi>SOLOMON</hi> ſaid in the old Teſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this is the ſumm of all,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Feare God and keep his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, this is the whole duty of man.</hi> So I ſay, to live rightly by faith, and to dye in hope, are the two chiefe leſſons of Chriſtianity. But becauſe they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law ſaw <hi>Chriſt</hi> like <hi>Moſes,</hi> in a veile, therfore was their leſſon legall, <hi>Fac hoc, et vive,</hi> do this and live. But ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi> was revealed, who is our life, we muſt find our life in him, that in our death we may find him with comfort. To this tendeth the whol Law and Goſpell. For this life was veil'd in the old Teſtament, and revealed in the new. To this life tend all the examples of the <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets,</hi> &amp; <hi>Apoſtles, which were written for our learning,</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119403:8"/>Rom. 15.4. of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> was not the leaſt, who could averre thus confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently of himſelfe, <hi>that to him to live was Christ, and to dye was gain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This bleſſed Apoſtle having ſaluted this Church of <hi>Philippi,</hi> with grace and peace, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. and having ſhewed them his thankefulneſſe to God, and his love to them, for the fruits of their faith, and fellowſhip of his ſufferings, (which he prayeth God to continue <hi>ver.</hi> 4.5. to the 9.) he makes in the next place an accompt to them of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſheweth them that the talent wherewith <hi>Chriſt</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted him, had encreaſed by his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings there, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>So that many wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed confident, to preach, as well as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ver.</hi> 14. <hi>though it may be ſome of envy, ſome of good will.</hi> All which he ſaith he knoweth ſhall turne to his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, according to his expectation, <hi>to magnify</hi> Chriſt <hi>in his body, whether by life or death, ver.</hi> 19.20. the reaſon of which confidence, this verſe ſheweth in theſe words, <hi>For to me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As if he ſhould have ſaid, If it pleaſe God, that I ſhall magnify Chriſt in my
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119403:8"/>body, living <hi>Chriſt</hi> is to me my way of living: or my life ſhall be ſpent to ſet forth, or ſet up the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It is life to me to do his worke, as you may perceive it to be expounded in the next verſe, <hi>If I live in the fleſh, that is, the fruit of my labour,</hi> viz. <hi>To advance the Kingdome of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>And to dye is gaine,</hi> becauſe I ſhall enjoy him for whom I laboured. But this is not ſo to all, yet to me it is, who deſire to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>Chriſt,</hi> both in my Life and Death, whom I finding to be my life, I know death muſt needs be my gain; becauſe thereby I receive the end of my hopes, the ſalvation of my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>There needs no accurate diviſion of theſe words, onely conſider theſe three things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, what is common to Chriſtians, and other creatures, To <hi>Live</hi> and <hi>Dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, What is proper in life and death to a true Chriſtian, beſides to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Firſt to find <hi>Chriſt to be their Life.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Death to be their gaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to find the fruit of this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, which is included in the word [FOR] having relation to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119403:9"/>verſe, which is a reſolution to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify God in his body, whether by Life or Death. Which fruit will alſo prove this aſſurance to be good, as all Gods graces are proved, or improved one by another. For upon ſuch a reſolution a man may well ſay, that Chriſt is his life and death his gain. For what life can ſtirre up this reſolution in a man, but the life of Chriſt onely? And what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage are we like to make by glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <hi>Chriſt</hi> in our bodies in life and death, if death yeeld not an advantage, when all is loſt in this world? But therefore he finding this fruit of reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhewes the reaſon of it thus, <hi>For to me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain.</hi> That makes me ſo bold to do as I ſay, and becauſe God hath given me grace to magnify <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I am no leſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, <hi>for Chriſt is life to me, and death advantage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> What is common to man, with other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. To Live.</note>Firſt, let us ſee what is common to man, with other creatures, <hi>(to wit)</hi> to <hi>live</hi> and <hi>dye.</hi> This is alſo common to all men, to <hi>Heathens</hi> as <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> To live is no priviledge, from the <hi>Ant,</hi> to the <hi>Elophant,</hi> every creature can boaſt as much, a Dog hath his day, a Flower
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119403:9"/>hath its flouriſh and fading, every leafe hath its ſpring and fall, and wherein doth a man exceed theſe, if he do but live? Nay, wherein do not theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in naturall life? For they have a certaine time of life, man hath not.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.1.</note> He that ſaid <hi>there was a time for all things,</hi> ſaid not <hi>there was a time to live.</hi> So they renew their age every yeare, but man is in a continuall decay, or decreaſe from his very birth.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.25, 26.</note> The Beaſts and he were made all upon one day, to forewarn him that he became not like one of them. But man remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not in honour,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 49.12</note> but became like the Beaſts that periſh. Nay worſe, <hi>He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth up, and is cut down like a flower.</hi> Wee ſcarce can peep out our heads, but Times Scyth is ready to mow us down, <hi>For all fleſh is graſſe,</hi> ſaith Iſaiah. It is not ſo good, our bodies are like baskets of duſt, which a little wind can ſcatter, and all our glory like a bladder of wind which the leaſt inciſion will ſoon emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
                  <p>What is there in life to boaſt of? but either
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Being,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Laſting,</hi> or</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A Seeming happy Accident.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119403:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Being.</note>Firſt, for a <hi>Being,</hi> It is not worth boaſting of, every <hi>Emmet</hi> hath an <hi>Eſſe,</hi> this makes a ſmall difference, let <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> teach them better, who boaſt of this, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.18. where he wiſheth that God would ſo manifeſt himſelfe to the ſons of men, that they who truſt to an <hi>Eſſe,</hi> or meer being, <hi>might ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be but Beaſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet ſome men are infinitely in love with life, why I know not. I thinke if they found as many checks in it as ſome doe, they would rather cry with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Eliah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 19.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord take me out of the world, that I may not ſee my wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> But it may be they know no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther happyneſſe, which makes them dote on this life, like Birds and Brutes, and onely dream of worldly felicity, as the <hi>Iews</hi> lookt for <hi>Chriſt</hi> in a temporall Kingdome, and as the <hi>Turkes</hi> did, and do looke for their great Prophet <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> who hath promiſed at his return to his Diſciples the world to enioy at pleaſure, and all other men to be their ſlaves. A doctrine taken up by ſome Chriſtians long ſince,<note place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>7.</hi> lib. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>as Ebion</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus,</hi> damnable Hereticks both; and by others of late, onely to keep up the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119403:10"/>lean hopes of their hungry followers, who gape but onely after carnall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (what ever they pretend to piety) if they can be bewitched by ſuch ſtuffe as this. Poore ſoules! All this is but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall being,<note place="margin">Micah 2.10.</note> which is not the place of your reſt, no more then your Lords Kingdome is of this world. But theſe kind of teachers have cozened you of your meat, and now for feare like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren you ſhould cry, and ſcratch, they fain would pleaſe you with a Puppet.</p>
                  <p>Beloved, Believe not every Spirit.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18, 19. Phil. 3.20</note> St. <hi>Iude</hi> tels you of dreamers. Be not led by a dreamer of dreames, nor be thou carryed away by high ſwelling words of vanity, by which the hearts of the ſimple are deceived. Look for Chriſt your life to appeare, but not according to the faſhion of this life. Prepare to meet the Lord in the aire,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.2.</note> not upon the earth, ſet not your mind on things that are beneath, but on the things that are above. Let no man ſpoil you of your reward, by thruſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into things he hath not ſeen, vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puffed up in his fleſhly mind. Let them enioy their thouſand yeares upon earth, without envy, look thou to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119403:11"/>Heaven forever.</p>
                  <p>For that thouſand yeares the <hi>Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries</hi> talk of ſo much,<note place="margin">Brightman on the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation.</note> taken from <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. is not any earthly Kingdome of Chriſt with his Saints. Becauſe it is called the firſt reſurrection, and ſeemeth to entail eternity onely upon thoſe who did enjoy it. Which if ſo, I pray what ſhall become of the reſt of the Saints, who ſhall ariſe after the thouſand years be paſt, who maintain the war againſt <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog?</hi> Are not they bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, though they did not partake of that thouſand yeares? Or are theſe the ſame Saints, which did enjoy the thouſand yeares? If ſo, then they muſt live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth more then a thouſand yeares, and ſo the truth of the 4th. verſe will be doubted. Or what ſhall become of the Saints, who never were beheaded for the teſtimony of Chriſt, and yet good Chriſtians? ſhall not they be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from death at the ſecond reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe of the firſt they could not partake, being no martyrs? <hi>Apage.</hi> I willtrouble you, nor my ſelfe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with raking in this mud.</p>
                  <p>Yet ſome love life more then theſe it ſeemes, who ſay that an evill Being is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119403:11"/>better then none at all. Firſt, becauſe (ſay they) a Being is good, but no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is no good. Secondly, becauſe a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing has a capability of exaltation, but no being hath none. Nay, ſome have been bold to ſay, that it is better to be in hell, then not to be at all; But there I leave them.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith that a <hi>nonens,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.3.</note> 
                     <hi>a not being, is better then them both,</hi> (viz.) <hi>who were oppreſſors, or were oppreſſed,</hi> though the one had power to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; which is a kind of unhappynes, and the other had no power to reſiſt it, which is a great miſery; ſo <hi>ver.</hi> 1. Yea,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.1.</note> he preferres it before them that were dead, <hi>whom yet he thinkes in better ſtate then the living,</hi> becauſe, <hi>the dead have had life, and loſt it: and the living are ſubject to vanity and mutability while they have it.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe ſaith <hi>Math.</hi> 26.24. <hi>It had been better for</hi> Iudas <hi>if he had never been born.</hi> For certainly, though that Being ſimply conſidered in it ſelfe, is better then not to be, yet it is not better to be in an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill condition, then not at all; becauſe that which was never had, was never loſt, and therefore no griefe vexeth one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119403:12"/>for that; But to be, and to be deprived of a good, is worſe then never to have it; Life ſimply conſidered, is but a way to death, therefore not to be doted upon.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond thing in living to be boaſted of,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Length of dayes.</note> is length of dayes, for if there be any good in life, the longer life we have, the better it is ſtill for us: But if nothing but vanity, then length of life is not worth boaſting of. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> therefore calls life, <hi>All the time of thy vanity, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.9. For indeed a man commeth in with <hi>vanity,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth with <hi>darknes;</hi> his life begins with <hi>ſports,</hi> and ends with <hi>griefes;</hi> like <hi>Venus</hi> Image, that ſeemed to ſmile up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that came into her Temple, but frown'd on all that went out; to ſhew that ſolace ends in ſorrow. Therefore ſaith that Wiſeman, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.3. <hi>If a man live an hundred yeares, and beget many children, and his ſoul be not ſatisfied with good, an untimely birth is better then he,</hi> becauſe it hath leſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of evill, and more reſt. Yet of this length of time many creatures can boaſt more then wee, as the <hi>Oake, Stag, Black-Bird,</hi> and the <hi>Raven,</hi> Every one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119403:12"/>of which if <hi>Naturians</hi> ſay true, can number hundreds of yeeres, onely you will ſay, they are obvious to chances more then you; yet therein we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for as a Bird is taken in the ſnare, and the Fiſh with a hooke, ſo is a man in the evill day, when it commeth ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly upon him. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.12. Beſides, every creature hath a power to hurt, as well as to help me, and any man that careth not for his own life, hath a kind of power over another mans. Surely then, long life being hazardous, is to live in doubt, and ſuſpend in feare, and therefore not to be boaſted of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>3</hi> Seeming happynes.</note>The third thing to be boaſted of in life, is the <hi>Accidents</hi> thereof, which conduce to ſome good in poſſibility at leaſt, ſuch as is <hi>Nobility, Power, Riches,</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> all which are ſubject to a change, or check.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Nobility</note>
                     <hi>Nobility</hi> is the finer meale, yet is the <hi>Common man</hi> and the <hi>Noble man</hi> ground all in one Mill of <hi>Nature.</hi> The <hi>rich</hi> and the <hi>poore</hi> meet together; the Lord is the maker of them both, <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.2. And it is a great check to <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> that it can neither it ſelfe hinder a Begger from riſing from the dunghill
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119403:13"/>to be ſet with Princes, nor prevent it ſelfe though cloathed in ſcarlet, from embracing the dunghill; It is but the moth of induſtry, and a bank upon which the Begger reſts, or on which the eyes of envy, like the Sun-beames, beate extreamly, even to the mouldring of it away to nothing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Power.</hi> 2. Pet. 2.19.</note>The other <hi>accident</hi> is <hi>Power,</hi> which while ſome men ſeek, they loſe <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and while they deſire to get power over others, they loſe it over them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and become ſervants either to <hi>Fame,</hi> or <hi>Buſines.</hi> In which when they have toyled themſelves, it comes to paſſe that they fall into diſgraces, as they firſt roſe by indignities; and though at their firſt riſing they ſeemed Lords of their Aſcendent, yet they prove darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their declining. Their ſtanding is ſlippery, and their failing melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and though their felicity ſtands much in other mens thoughts, yet they ſhall not have my opinion to make them happy, becauſe I perceive they are dying every day, but have no leiſure to thinke of it, yet they firſt find their griefes, but laſt (if not too late) ſee their errours.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119403:13"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>3.</hi> Riches.</note>Another <hi>Accident</hi> of life is wealth, or Riches, which are a ſtrong hold in a mans imagination, yet will prove hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ranſome for a mans life,<note place="margin">Pro. 18.11.</note> ſometimes either to the Phyſitian or the Souldier; What happyneſſe is there in that, whoſe reall uſe is but rightly to leave it? Which whoſoever doth not, is but bought and ſold with his own money. I am ſure the ancient Wiſe men called them <hi>irritamenta malorum,</hi> the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to evil, and they prove <hi>impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta virtutum,</hi> the impediments of vertue. I confeſſe them to be <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula vitae,</hi> props to this fraile life of ours, leſt wee ſhould loath it, but not ſuch additaments as may make us love it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>4.</hi> Friends.</note>Fourthly, <hi>Friends,</hi> are the laſt good <hi>accident</hi> of life, without whom wee live like beaſts in a wood; they multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all our joyes, and divide our griefes when wee impart them; But when I conſider amongſt ſo many friends there be ſo few true, life ſeemes tedious as to <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jerem. 9.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Oh, that I had a Cottage in the Wilderneſſe, that I might flee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the aſſembly of treacherous men!</hi> For men without true friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119403:14"/>are but like pictures in a room, fair and uſeleſſe.</p>
                  <p>Yet there be other concomitants of life, which ſeem to give ſome content; for though all other degenerate, as <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> into <hi>ſervility, Riches</hi> to <hi>Beggery, Power</hi> into <hi>Tyranny, Friendſhip</hi> to <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> by which life is imbitter'd; yet there be <hi>vertues</hi> which better, and <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> which ſublime life, to a <hi>ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> condition, even while we live here in this tabernacle of fleſh. Yet when I ſee even theſe have their mixtures of imperfection, and that the <hi>Epiphonema</hi> of them,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.19.</note> is above ſummed up in our my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> under whom, we and they muſt be reduced; and when I ſee that many who thinke they ſtand, are apt to fall, and with <hi>Demas,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the preſent world, though it may be with <hi>David</hi> they thought they ſhould never be moved, then do I wiſh for the wings of a Dove, to flee away and be at reſt, for who can ſet his mind on that which is unſettled? For as life is but <hi>manſio animae in corpore, the ſojourning of the ſoule in the body,</hi> which is apt to remove: ſo to live long, is but <hi>Reman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura,</hi> a little longer ſtay then ordinary,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119403:14"/>and that in bonds. For <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the body is but a ſhackle to the ſoule. His fleſh is called by the <hi>Hebrews</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>lecham,</hi> bread, becauſe bread for wormes, as <hi>Abenezra,</hi> and other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from <hi>Iob</hi> 20.23. in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. So <hi>Senex</hi> is but <hi>Seminex,</hi> an old man is like one halfe dead,<note place="margin">Jam. 3.6.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, generation, is ſo called, becauſe it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an intruſion into the earth, which muſt have an extruſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. One Generation goeth and another commeth. St. <hi>Iames</hi> cals it a wheel, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a courſe of nature, which goeth alwaies round; a thing well obſerved by a King, that drew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others the chariot of <hi>Seleſtris,</hi> whom the Tyrant asking what he ayl'd to looke back ſo often upon the chariot wheel, anſwered, to obſerve how that Spoke which is now uppermoſt, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non depreſt in the dirt; which anſwer made the Tyrant more mild after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  <p>It is indeed but a vapour, of which there is no hold, therefore ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Ne glorieris in craſtinum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 27.1.</note> 
                     <hi>boaſt not of to morrow, thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth.</hi> Being, without
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119403:15"/>well-being, is not worth our deſires, wee muſt looke to another life, if wee deſire to ſee good dayes, and that is the life <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> which doth difference our lives from all others, <hi>For our life is hid with Chriſt in God.</hi> Coloſſ. 3.3. and from this life wee are denominated, as righteouſneſſe doth a righteous man, for as <hi>Non vivere ſed valere eſt vita,</hi> not to live but to be in health is life, the reſt is ſicknes, and deaths equipage: ſo not to live is a Chriſtian life, but to live godly. God lookes <hi>Non tam multum, ſed quam bene,</hi> not how long, but how well wee live, there is therefore not onely a life naturall, but a life ſpirituall, which prepares us for a life eternall, as the wildernes of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> did lead to <hi>Canaan.</hi> This is when wee lead a naturall life after a ſpirituall manner, as to be a <hi>Mary</hi> in contemplation, and ſo anticipate the joyes of heaven; or a <hi>Martha,</hi> by good actions, and ſo become our own rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, by laying up for our ſelves a good foundation, againſt the time to come, that wee may lay hold of eternall life, or like <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to come out of the grave at the call of Chriſt, or to make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119403:15"/>Chriſt our pattern, who hath left us an example, that wee ſhould follow his ſteps, or like St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to make Chriſt our life, that death may be our gain.</p>
                  <p>So I come to that life, which puts a difference between other men,<note place="margin">The life different of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> and a Chriſtian, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to be their life. Of this St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, who made not the world his life, nor his pleaſure his life, but as the worke of Chriſt was his meat and drinke, ſo Chriſt was his life alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> This may be underſtood, <hi>Operativè,</hi> Or <hi>Objectivè.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, Operatively, that is, if I live, Chriſt is my life, by the operation of faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I live, yet not I, but</hi> Chriſt <hi>liveth in me, and the life that I now live, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelfe for me.</hi> For Chriſt lives in a man by his Spirit, by faith and by love.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by his Spirit, juſtifying me, that his righteouſnes is mine in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of it; that he hath deſerved for me to be held guiltleſſe of all ſin in the ſight of God; ſo by his ſpirit alſo ſanctifying me,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119403:16"/>to a new and true ſpirituall obedience: &amp; laſtly,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16</note> exciting me by the ſame ſpirit, to every good worke. To this purpoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſpirit witneſſeth to our ſpirits, that wee are the ſons of God.</hi> This is <hi>Pignus ſalutis, the pledge of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg.</note> which never goeth alone without the other, <hi>for that ſpirit that gives the pledge of ſalvation, giveth alſo the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bur vitae, <hi>the ſtrength of life,</hi> by which thoſe things are eaſie which before ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med hard: and laſtly, <hi>Lumen ſcientiae,</hi> the life of knowledge, which like light doth illuminate what was darke, and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth what lay hid in our earthy natures.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Chriſt lives in me by faith, urging me to believe, that by his grace I am that I am.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, He lives in me by love, by which fayth worketh me, firſt, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe to be his in all true obliegement, and then to do him all manner of ſervice. Therefore St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> prayeth to God, that his ſpirit may thus live in him, <hi>Sanctum ſemper opus in me ſpira ut cogitem, ſuade ut diligam, urge ut faciam,</hi> inſpire me with thy holy worke, perſwade me to love, urge me to do.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119403:16"/>
                  <p>And ſo comes in the ſecond ſence of this text, <hi>viz. Objectivè,</hi> which I take to be here eſpecially meant, namely, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt,</hi> that is, I accompt my life Chriſts, to be ſpent and diſpoſed of in him, and for him, to be ſpent in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.16. <hi>I am thy ſervant.</hi> So all the Apoſtles write themſelves, CHRISTS and the CHURCHES ſervants, the <hi>Pope</hi> writes himſelfe ſo, but tis meerly ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular, he Lords it too much over Gods inheritance, to be a ſervant. This is a good Chriſtian complement, when it is eſſentiall, that whether wee live, wee live to to the Lord, or whether wee dye,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.8</note> wee dye to the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>To live to me is Chriſt,</hi> if my life be willingly at his diſpoſall, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. <hi>I am not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy onely to be bound, but to dye for the Lord Ieſus;</hi> ſo that here we ſee, if Chriſt be our life, then our life muſt be Chriſts, the one of theſe depends upon the other, Chriſt hath bought us, wee are not our owne, <hi>Glorifie therefore</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>God in your bodies, and in your ſpirits, for they are Gods.</hi> Wee muſt not live to our ſelves,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20 2 Cor. 5.15</note> let us firſt find that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119403:17"/>Chriſt is our life, &amp; then the other wil be found alſo, that our life ſhall be Chriſts, for ſuch an unionthere is between Chriſt and us, as there is between the Head and the Members, the Vine and the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; If the Body have a living Head, the ſenſe of the Body is derived from the Head, and diſpoſed of to the good of the Head; and therfore here is ſet down, that Chriſt is to me life, becauſe Chriſt is all in all to them that are his, in the <hi>flux,</hi> &amp; <hi>reflux</hi> of grace, in the preventing &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating; in the donation, and retribution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> How ſhall I know Chriſt to be in me, that I may ſay comfortably to my ſelfe, <hi>That Chriſt is life to me?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label>
                     <hi>By the Spirit that he hath given us.</hi> 1. Joh. 3.24. which Spirit is known by divers motions.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by a purpoſe to obey God, and an inclination to that purpoſe; Therefore Chriſt minded Gods work with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 4.34.</note> more then his dayly food, and he was ſtraitned till that was accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that he was ſent to ſuffer; but you muſt obſerve, this purpoſe and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in us, not onely in extremities, as in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exo. 9.28.</note> while the rod was upon him, he promiſed fair; but even while we are
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119403:17"/>in health, and have the world at will; God loves to be choſen as freely, as he was forſaken; and it is a great comfort to a man, and a good token of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when a man can ſay, This good I did embrace, and this evill I did forſake, meerely for Gods cauſe, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect or conſtraint, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did,<note place="margin">Gen. 39 9.</note> 
                     <hi>How can I do this great wickednes, and ſin againſt God?</hi> The Devil (as the Proverb is) when he was ſick would be a <hi>Monke,</hi> (which ſavours of more religion, then thoſe <hi>Monkes,</hi> who while they be well, will be devils) but being well he was the devill ſtill; ſo many of us, cry in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and pretend repentance, but the ſtorme being over, we doe as he did, that vowed to a Saint, if he came ſafe to ſhore, a wax Candle of twelve pound weight, but when he came there, he gave one of twelve in the pound.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The other ſign of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is to have the mind of Chriſt, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much urgeth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Let the ſame mind be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt:</hi> the ſpirit of God appeared like a <hi>Dove,</hi> like a <hi>Fire,</hi> and like a <hi>tongne;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 3.16. Act. 2.3.</note> a <hi>Dove,</hi> to ſhew ſimplicity, a <hi>Fire,</hi> to ſhew ardency, and a <hi>Tongue,</hi> to ſhew
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119403:18"/>it loved to informe ignorance. So did Chriſt, he did no harm, but much good, <hi>and the zeal of Gods houſe did even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume him,</hi> and his tongue never ceaſed to preach the glad tidings of ſalvation; ſee then, if you have pure <hi>ſimplicity,</hi> without <hi>hypocriſie, zeal</hi> without <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> or <hi>partiality,</hi> and a <hi>tongue</hi> ready to glorifie God, then ſure Chriſt is your life.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the third ſign is to love Chriſt for himſelfe, and all thoſe that love Chriſt, though I know not their perſons, or if I do, yet to love them for this reaſon onely, becauſe they love Chriſt, <hi>Thus wee paſſe from death to life, if wee love the brethren.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.14. <hi>And that it be</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation,</hi> Rom. 12.9.</p>
                  <p>But before wee paſſe to that life, there is a vale of death to be paſſed, which though it be common to all, yet it is not advantagious to all, but onely to ſuch, to whom Chriſt is life; therefore wee will firſt looke upon it as it is common to all, then, how it is a peculiar benefit to ſome.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Death is common to all, <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum eſt omnibus ſemel mori, It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119403:18"/>unto all men once to dye,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23</note> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, <hi>Man ſinned, and the wages of ſin is death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> But ſome will ſay, if man had not ſinned, yet he would have dyed, becauſe no body conſiſting of elements can be eternall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> Wee anſwer, that this is more then can be proved, for though it be true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Philoſophy, yet it will make no axiome in Divinity, for wee muſt know that Phyloſophers ſpoke accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the effects which ſinne had brought upon the creature, and to that eſtate in which the offence left man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, which ſin it may be was unknown to the Phyloſophers. Beſides, we find death to be the iſſue of ſin, <hi>And threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely for ſin;</hi> and therefore ſurely had not <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> he had not been mortall. Beſides, a change might have been without death, as wee ſee in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers creatures, the <hi>Eagle</hi> by caſting or breaking off her Bill, the <hi>Snake,</hi> by ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off his old rugged skin, becomes more lively and active. Laſtly, the <hi>Tree</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> for ought we know, might be as well <hi>reſtaurative,</hi> as <hi>ſacramental,</hi> an help to <hi>Nature,</hi> as well as a type of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119403:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                     </label> Why then do other creatures dye, which ſinned not?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> They are ſubjected to vanity for our ſakes, <hi>They were made for man,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for man ſubjected,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.20</note> that man by them might be ſerved, and not ſtarved for want of them, therefore there is no injury done to the creature by God, but by man, when he doth abuſe them by cruelty or ſurquedry.</p>
                  <p>Therefore being that to dye is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to man, it behooves man to expect it,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.43</note> &amp; to ſuſpect it, as a thiefe that would ſteal upon him, this contemplation, when it proceeds not from Panick feare, is holy and pious, I mean when I do not feare death ſo much, as a debt of nature, but as the wages of ſin; for ſo to fear it is childiſh, for many go out of the world eaſier then they came in, and the vitall parts are not ſo quick of ſenſe, as other parts are; therefore a religious fear of death is profitable, becauſe it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares us to dye, by making us to caſt up our accompt, and make all even before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> 
                     <hi>And to judge our ſelves, that wee may not be judged;</hi> that ſo as by ſin, wee have made life away unto death, ſo by a true preparation we may make death a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119403:19"/>paſſage to everlaſting life; for, as ſaith S. <hi>Bernard, Cecidimus omnes ſuper lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in luto, unde inquinati, et vulnerati ſumus, Wee are fallen upon a ſtone in the dirt, by which wee are both defiled and wounded;</hi> wee muſt therefore before wee dye, be waſhed in the laver of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and cured by the blood of the Covenant.</p>
                  <p>There be three ſorts of People, can never prepare well for death. The firſt is the <hi>Epicure</hi> and <hi>Socinian,</hi> who deny the ſoules immortality: ſuch were in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time, who ſaid, <hi>Let us eate and drinke, for to morrow wee ſhall dye;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.32.</note> and though that theſe thought of no reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at all, yet it will not excuſe them, who imagine the ſoule to have no ſubſiſting after this life, as to be capable either of joy or ſorrow, and therefore they count the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſ Steg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Diſp.</note> not to be a thing propounded in a figure, which may have a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding reddition, but a meer fiction, as of the Poets <hi>Tartarus</hi> and <hi>Elyſium,</hi> whom the <hi>Popes</hi> policy in ſetting up <hi>Purgatory</hi> will condemn to have leſſereligion then himſelfe: theſe men can never prepare for death, but rather for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119403:20"/>of life, becauſe with death their happyneſſe ends, like a birds, or a beaſts.</p>
                  <p>But this error is confuted divers wayes. Firſt, from the very inſtinct of nature, which deſires perpetuity of name, fame,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.18.</note> and family, which is but the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of eternity in the ſoule; ſo alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſoul is no bodyly thing, and therefore not corruptible, it finds no ſatisfaction in finite things, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, except it be made in vain, cannot ceaſe to be, till it hath enjoyed the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject adequated to it,<note place="margin">Greg. Nyſſ.</note> and then it can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe that object doth quicken it the more, for the viſion of God is the life of the ſoule, which viſion it appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth, when it is ſeparated from the body, therefore God is ſaid to be the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 12.27</note> of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> though they were dead, becauſe they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to him;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.23</note> ſo in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the 12. and 23. there is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, which muſt needs be in heaven, by the ſight of God, though their bodyes be not yet raiſed. If wee thinke not thus, how ſhall wee prepare to leave the certainty wee have here, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119403:20"/>enjoy we know not what, nor when?</p>
                  <p>Nor doe they rightly prepare for death, who ſleight it; for it is the King of terrours. It is not putting on the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant bravery of a Roman ſpirit, who knowes not what comes after, that gives Death right entertainment. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate reſolutions, are not heroicall Chriſtian vertues. For ſee revenge of wrongs dares death; a man in griefe wooes death; and the feare of dying, hath prevented the cruelty of it. Some have dyed in pittying of others, as ſome of <hi>Otho's</hi> friends did. And Chriſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples had a touch of this, when they ſaid, (hearing <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead) <hi>Let us goe, that we may die with him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 11.16</note> Love ſleights death. A certaine Neapolitane leapt into the Sea, when his wife was taken by Pyrates. <hi>Tiberius Graocus</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving two ſnakes in his houſe, male and female, was told by the Southſayer, that if he killed the female, his wife ſhould die; if the male, himſelfe ſhould: He kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the male, and dyed firſt himſelfe. <hi>Beauxamonts</hi> wife the Moore, would be buryed with her husband. <hi>Porcia,</hi> the wife of <hi>Brutus,</hi> dyed by eating hot bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning coales, for griefe her husband was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119403:21"/>dead. But all theſe ſorrowed as men without hope, and did not prepare for death, but provoked him againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Others of the Heathen dyed with leſſe paſſion, though for ought I know, with as little hope. As great <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> in a faire complement with <hi>Livia: Conjugii noſtrimemor eſto, vive, &amp; vale:</hi> ſaying, Be mindfull, <hi>Livia,</hi> of our wedlock bands, live ſtill, and proſper. But there is more to be done in this buſineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt therefore, be acquainted with death, by dying to one ſinne or other that liveth in thee, or by killing that love to the world, eaſe, riches, friends, which makes death ſo bitter, as ſaith <hi>Syracides,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ecclus. 41.1</note> 
                     <hi>O Death, how bitter is thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance to a man that lives at eaſe in his poſſeſſions!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, be temperate in all things againſt this fight. So the Apoſtle coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.25</note> 
                     <hi>(They that ſtrive for masteries, are temperate in all things)</hi> leſt when he comes to fight, you are loth to loſe your delicates: as many are loth to die, ſo long as they can but receive meat. Theſe are ſuch who make their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119403:21"/>their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. For banquetting is <hi>vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum animae,</hi> the bond of the ſoule, and the fetters of the affections. As we read of <hi>Philoxenus,</hi> who would not leave the <hi>Polypus</hi> his head behind him, though his Phyſitian told him, that what he had eat already, would kill him in ſeven houres. Many there are, <hi>Qui Curios ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulant,</hi> who ſeeme abſtemious a while, (yet ſcarce a Faſting day) but like the fiſh <hi>Muſipula,</hi> they ſuck up their frie againe, which they had formerly vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Challenge death in thy ſhirt, ſtrip thee naked of all worldly habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. He fights but as ſome Souldiers doe, for booty. If he finde nothing to ſpoile thee of, he hath no ſpirit to fight with thee. <hi>Job</hi> wooed him to wound him, but he would not.<note place="margin">Job 4.13</note> It is our hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the world, which makes death violent; and our ſecurity, that makes him ſo eager to obtain a <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi> But if he finde a man, that, <hi>Nil niſi cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem morti conceſſerit atrae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horat.</note> who has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for death but his skin, he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to let him alone, till ſome better advantage happen to his liking.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, yet doe not take deaths part
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119403:22"/>againſt thy ſelfe, by lying at too open a ward of deſpair. For that is it he would have, and therefore makes thee beleeve, that he will end all thy paine and grief, ſhame and ſorrows, if thou wilt betray thy life unto him, by ſome violent death. Whereas indeed, then begins thy miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for while there is life there is hope. <hi>I waited long, and at the laſt God heard me, Pſal.</hi> 40.1. Know ye not, that <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 1.12.</note> for he ſhall receive at laſt a crown that fadeth not away. You muſt like a faithfull Sentinell, wait till your change come. No Souldier is praiſed for march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without the word of command; nor no Chriſtian, for ſpending his life, till God take it. I read of a Roman Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that whipt a builder for uſing other timber then he had appointed, though (it may be) more fit for the purpoſe. If a practicall Carpenter, was ſo ſerved, wanting onely the complement of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; what have your pragmaticall builders deſerved, who out of the ſpirit of diſobedience, will have no cake but of <hi>Thamars</hi> making, though it prove their owne ruine? Well, let us not call death upon our ſelves by the errour of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119403:22"/>our lives, but prepare onely for it. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcas vivere oportet, ſi diſcas mori:</hi> You muſt forget to live, if you would learne to die, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, who ſaid, <hi>By the rejoycing I have in Chriſt Jeſus, I thanke God I die daily,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31.</p>
                  <p>Nor count death evill, as thoſe that dye without hope, as one <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> of whom <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, He was of ſo weak a heart, that he would refuſe no torment, <hi>Nec acutam crucem, dummodo inter haec mala, ſpiritus &amp; vita prorogentur.</hi> He was content to endure any torment, ſo his life might be prolonged. Which, ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> was <hi>peſſimum votum,</hi> the worſt deſire and wiſh, and argued him effeminate and baſe. <hi>Quia diſtulit id quod eſt in malis optimum, ſupplicii fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> becauſe Death is the end of all miſery and puniſhment. Yet the man could not be much blamed, not knowing with <hi>Adrian,</hi> what life was to come after, whether any, or none: Which made him ſo diſcourſe with his ſoule, <hi>Animula, vagra, blanda, quae nunc abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis in loca!</hi> Little vagrant tender ſoule, into what regions art thou poſting hence? And indeed if we know not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119403:23"/>that, I wonder not to ſee folké loth to die; for <hi>a living dog is better then a dead lion.</hi> But death is not evill in it ſelfe, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Not to die is evill, but to die ill is evill. Which that we may not doe, wee muſt ſo prepare our ſelves, that we may look back upon our lives with comfort, and forward upon the object of our hope with joy, that ſo it may prove an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to us.</p>
                  <p>So I come to the other thing in death, which is proper to a true Chriſtian. <hi>(viz.)</hi> a Gaine. <hi>Death is to me a gaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                     </label> Death is a privation, therefore a loſſe; How is it then a gaine?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                     </label> Not in it ſelf, but in regard of the over-ruling power of Chriſt, who hath conquered him, and altered his nature; ſo that of a privation, it is become but a commutation, from a loſſe to a <hi>gaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore thoſe that live to Chriſt, loſe nothing by death, but gaine by it. All things elſe loſe by it, as either life, or pleaſure, or wealth. But all theſe are gained by a good man in death: firſt, life, Chriſt came, that wee might have it more abundantly. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.10. And for pleaſure and joy, <hi>In his preſence is the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119403:23"/>fulneſſe of joy, and at his right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Pſal. 16.11. And for wealth, there is no want:<note place="margin">Luk. 12.32</note> Wee change a Cottage for a Court, and a Farme for a Kingdome. This is not hard to prove, if we could beleeve Scripture, which tells us, <hi>that no eye hath ſeen, nor care heard, nor tongue is able to expreſſe, what God hath laid up for them that love him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us of a <hi>crowne of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> of a <hi>weight;</hi> yea, an <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting weight of glory.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.17. Now it is not ſo in this life; For all that wee have here, is either toilſome to get, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to keep, or fulſome to continue with, as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith of ſatiety. <hi>Cogita quamdiu eadem feceris Mori, velle non tantum fortis &amp; miſer, ſed etiam faſtidio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus poteſt.</hi> A man would die with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe of reiterating the ſame thing, though he were neither valiant nor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. The beſt thing here, is of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing nature, but our inheritance there, is incorruptible, undefiled, and fadeth not away, and reſerved in heaven where there is no feare of robbing,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.4.</note> or ſpoiling us of it, either by the violence of the Souldier, or the craſt of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, or the deceitfulneſſe of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119403:24"/>But all things here are fading, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Grace, and yet that hath much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe to ſtick by us, as ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, I find a Law in my members, fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of my mind.</hi> Rom. 7.23.</p>
                  <p>Who feels or ſees not this decay, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thoſe whoſe eyes are too much fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the worlds toyes, <hi>whom the god of this world hath blinded? Excellens ſenſibile deſtruit ſenſum.</hi> They look too much much on the world, and ſo are blinded by it. They hold it not at a juſt diſtance from God and Godlineſſe, or look not upon it with a right ſpectacle of Gods Word, which diſcovers to us all her adulterate ware. That is the Reaſon, why we ſee not the envie of honour, the allurements of pleaſure, the inconſtancy of riches, the impediments of Poverty, the temptings of the fleſh, the baits of beautie, the infirmities of the body, the certainty of evill, and the danger of loſing good.</p>
                  <p>What then is all this to what wee loſe by being abſent from the Lord, whilſt we are in the body?<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.6.</note> Wee loſe the bleſſed viſion, the ſight of God, the preſence of Chriſt, the full enjoyment of the holy Ghoſt, the company of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119403:24"/>and the Society of Saints; all which we know but in part here, but then we ſhall know, even as we are knowne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> To enſure your ſelf hereof, look you that you have the fruit of this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that Chriſt is your life,<note place="margin">The fruit of this confidence</note> and death is your gaine, included in the word <hi>(For,)</hi> which hath relation to that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, which this confidence bred, namely, to glorifie God in his body, whether by life or death, becauſe Chriſt was his life, and death was to him ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. And ſurely, hee that deſireth ſo to doe, cannot chuſe but find the other; For Chriſt being his life, makes him apt to glorifie God in life, and in death; And this he reſolving to doe, muſt needs produce this effect, that death muſt be his gain. For <hi>he that will loſe his life for my ſake, ſhall find it,</hi> Mat. 10.39. And not ſuch a life ſimply; but bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an hundred fold in the happineſſe of it, and for the continuance everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>The ſumme then of all is this: Conſider we are Chriſtians, which doth give us a right to a better life then nature can, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſpirituall life in Chriſt, and an eternall life with Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119403:25"/>
                  <p>To obtain either of theſe, we muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the voluptuouſnes of life naturall, and let Chriſt be our contemplation, and his example our pattern. This is <hi>in mundo vivere, &amp; vana mundi contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere;</hi> to live in the world,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe it; to uſe the world, as not uſing it. The world muſt be crucified to me, as looking on it as a curſed thing. <hi>Totus mundus poſitus in maligno;</hi> and I muſt be crucified to the world by its hatred of me. So that we muſt live as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> directs, our <hi>loynes girded with truth, lamps burning in our hand, viz.</hi> ſhining in good workes; and laſtly, watching in devotion, leſt we be found ſleeping.</p>
                  <p>This being done, we may bid death welcome, for he brings advantage with him. And if yet our infirmities pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death formidable, Conſider, what is death; but a fall to riſe like the ſetting of the Sunne, A medicine to thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which ſinne brought upon us. For we, having fallen by ſinne into all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of woe, it was mercy as well as Juſtice in God, to make us mortall, leſt we ſhould live for ever miſerable, <hi>Pluto</hi> gueſſed well, when he ſaid, <hi>Death was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119403:25"/>the Law of Nature. Adrian</hi> ſaid better, and more full, that Death was <hi>Paver divitum, pauper is defiderium;</hi> the feare of the rich, and the deſire of the poore. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid more divinely, that it was <hi>Finis,</hi> or <hi>Tranſitus,</hi> an end to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mans happineſſe, a paſſage to the good mans bleſſedneſſe. Death cannot bite Innocence, but ſmiles upon it. Which made Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to ſay, He deſired to ſee death as Chriſt had made it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, conſider not ſo much the ſeares it has, as the joyes it brings. It is ſtrange to ſee, how light they made of it, who had no ſuch hopes as we have, I meane the Heathen. And we that count our ſelves the true Iſraelites, need not be aſhamed to borrow a jewel of theſe Egyptians. <hi>Cato</hi> ſent <hi>Caeſar</hi> word, that he feared more his pardon then his pain. The joyes of death are ſuch to thoſe that live well, as that they rejoyce, when it draweth nigh: For it is but a ſleep, and the grave a dormitorie, where <hi>men reſt from their labours. In vitâ vigilant juſti, ideo in morte dicuntur dormire,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Righteous men watch while they live, and therefore
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119403:26"/>are ſaid to ſleep when they be dead. A certaine wiſe Roman ſaid, <hi>Non puera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcam, ſi Deus mihi largiatur:</hi> He would not be a child again, though God would permit it; His reaſon was, becauſe now (ſayes he) <hi>Ex hoſpitio ad domum diſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> I ſhall goe from my Inne to my home. For indeed, the ſoule, <hi>Non eſt, ubi nunc eſt,</hi> is not where it would be: It looks <hi>ad futura,</hi> to that which is to come. And he that doth not, beleeves not certainly the ſoules immortality, nor the paine of death; which being once apprehended, makes us impatient to live in <hi>Meſech,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 120.5.</note> and deſirous of <hi>diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> with S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which gaine if thou wouldeſt make of death, die to the world betimes. He that begins a journey early makes a pleaſure of it, rather then a paine. Such men are neither aſhamed to live, becauſe they have lived well; nor affraid to die, becauſe they are are but going whither they have beene alwaies travelling. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> therefore <hi>thy Creatour in the daies of thy youth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note> 
                     <hi>before the evill day come.</hi> Like the Bee and the Ant, let not your proviſion be to make in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Chriſt taught us to prevent impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119403:26"/>of ſafety, when he ſaid to the people concerning the deſtruction of Jeruſalem, <hi>pray,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 25.20</note> 
                     <hi>that your flight be not in the winter, nor on the Sabbath day,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee knew their opinion of the Sabbath, would hinder their flight one way, as the winter another. So pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt this bluſtring day of death, leſt it hinder you in your paſſage to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. In a word, let ſin die before thee, and then it cannot follow thee to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Feare not death, but looke to the errour of your life, break off ſinne by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and entertaine Chriſt, and death will be found without ſting; yea, no croſſe but a crowne, no dart, but a ſcepter, ſhalt thou find in Chriſts hand, or an olive in token of our victorie. As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently thou maiſt paſſe deaths teeth, as once <hi>Ignat.</hi> did the teeth of wild beaſts, who ſaid before hand, when he was condemned; <hi>I care not what death I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, for ſeeing I am Gods corn, I care not with what flaile of death he pleaſe to beat me out, for I am willing to beground, even by the teeth of theſe beaſts; that I may make cleane bread for Chriſt, who became the bread of life for me.</hi> How cheerfully may we then ſay, <hi>Egredere
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119403:27"/>anima mea, egredere:</hi> Goe forth my Soul,<note place="margin">Pſ. 142.9.</note> to meet thy Saviour, &amp; with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> pray, <hi>Lord bring my ſoul out of</hi> this <hi>priſon, that I may praiſe thy Name.</hi> And with Saint <hi>Aug. Creaſti nos ob te,</hi> and Lord thou haſt created us for thy ſelfe, and I cannot be quiet til I come to thee. And then ſhall begin that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Epithalamium,</hi> or wedding ſong of foure parts, ſung in Antiphona's and Reſponſories, <hi>The Lamb ſaith Come, and the Spirit ſaith, Come, and the Bride ſaith, Come, and thy ſoule ſhall ſay, Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So did this our deceaſed Siſter, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> MARY OVERMAN, deſcended of an ancient and worthy Family of the <hi>Breretons,</hi> marryed into an accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Family of the <hi>Overmans,</hi> with whom though ſhe found ſufficiencie and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to her owne hearts deſire, yet ſhe breathed after another life: Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was ſullenly faln out of love with the world, but in love with Chriſt, as appeared by her dying words, which muſt eternize her memory, when as a little before her diſſolution, this earneſt and pious prayer departed from her firſt, <hi>Lord when ſhall I come and appear before
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119403:27"/>the preſence of Chriſt, my JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S?</hi> Dying MARY it ſeemes by this was ready for living CHRIST, and living CHRIST as willing to receive dying MARY; for ſoone after, he took her to himſelfe: Who though ſhe was weak in body, yet was ſhe ſtrong in faith and hope; which <hi>viaticum</hi> ſhe had with her to ſtrengthen her in her jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and to convey her ſoule into the hands of her Redeemer. Herein as well approving as profeſſing her ſelfe a true MARY, in <hi>chooſing that better part, which</hi> now <hi>ſhall never be taken from her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next to Chriſt her Head in heaven, ſhe loved her Head on earth, whom God had given her; and like the Turtle, loved her Mate: yet was not like <hi>Rachel,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate for children, nor yet dejected for want of them.</p>
                  <p>She ſpent her time not idly, (as many of her degree too uſually doe even in theſe times, whoſe miſeries call to <hi>bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>ſackcloth</hi>) but like another <hi>Dorcas</hi> ſhe ſeemed to thoſe that have ſeene her conſtant employment, ſo farre from being idle, that ſhe was moſt an end well buſied, and full of good works.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119403:28"/>So that as it was written of the Ladie <hi>Paula,</hi> ſo it may be of Her too, that ſhe ſpent moſt of her time, either in good workes, or Gods worſhip. Her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was not onely a ſhop of Confection (as the faſhion is) but an Oratorie for Devotion.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, In a long and tedious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, ſhe behaved her ſelfe very patiently; and knowing under whoſe hand ſhe ſuffered, opened not her mouth in any diſcontent, and well perceiving it was the Lords doing thus to permit her to ſuffer, ſhe laid her downe and poſſeſt her ſoule in patience; only with the meeke ſpirit of <hi>Iob,</hi> intending Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to imitate him in this her ſanctified affliction, in the depth of her conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet in the height of her devotion, applyed ever and anon <hi>Jobs</hi> deploring words to her languiſhing ſelfe, and like him, wholy ſubmitting her ſelfe to Gods diſpoall, ſaid, <hi>My months are moneths of vanity, and ſad nights are appointed for me.</hi> And at other times in <hi>Davids</hi> words, (for ſhe converſed much with dead Saints, whiles ſhe was living, and had therefore learnt to uſe their language now ſhe was dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119403:28"/>when in his prayer, he deciphered his miſeries, that he might the eaſier implore mercy, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 31.10. <hi>My life is conſumed with greif, and my years with ſighing.</hi> So that as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid, of one dying of ſuch a diſeaſe, ſo may we of hers, that it ſeemd a martyrdome.</p>
                  <p>Yet was ſhe not childiſhly afraid of death, nor ſtruggled ſhe much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine life, as ſome doe, from whom God is faine, as it were, to teare away their ſoules; but ſhe offered up hers as a free-will-offering, with a contempt of the world, ſaying, <hi>Away with all theſe things,</hi> and with an earneſt deſire beſides to be with Chriſt, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene her life, made death her gaine. Which Text it ſeemes was ſome time ſince her owne meditation, as appeares by her notes under her owne hand, with this her devout paraphraſe found upon them, <hi>Heaven is my home, I am a ſtranger here:</hi> Which undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly was the language of her heart, as well as of her hand. And if ſo, what can we leſſe perſwade our ſelves ſhe is, then what ſhe made her ſelfe by her pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous endeavours, a true, a very MARY,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119403:29"/>that is, by interpretation, <hi>Excellent.</hi> Excellent in Contemplation, thereby anticipating the joyes of heaven whilſt ſhe walkt upon the earth, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in action too, her actions ſpeaking her a perfect ſervant of the Almighty: And therefore now no doubt after death, a partaker of his glory with her fellow Saints, for right dear in the ſight of the Lord is the death of ſuch Saints, ſo deare that he takes them into his boſome.</p>
                  <p>And for our parts, we may ſay of her, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaid of <hi>Fabiola, Ex annulo Eccleſiae monile perdidimus,</hi> We, even wee have loſt a precious jewell out of the Ring of the Church. But loſt ſhe is not (I doe her wrong to ſay ſo of her) whom God hath found. She is not dead, but ſleepeth. And her fleſh doth reſt in hope, that what is ſowne in weakneſſe ſhall riſe in power, according to his mightie working, who is able to ſubdue all things unto himſelfe, who bringeth downe to the grave, and raiſeth up, by whom death is already ſwallowed up in victorie, and ſo made an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to us.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119403:29"/>
                  <p>Thus paſſed this precious Saint from ſickneſſe to perfect health, from weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to perfect ſtrength, from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to perfect freedome, from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perfect peace, from loſſe to perfect gaine, from heavineſſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect joyes. In a word, ſhe is paſſed from death to life, and from earth to heaven, to be for ever in perfect hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, where wee leave her ſafe, and come to cloze with you.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore as the death of Chriſt doth for us make a gaine of death; ſo may the death of good men and women, worke ſome advantage alſo for us in that point, and ſo their death may be a gaine to us. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.2</note> 
                     <hi>It is better to goe into the houſe of mourning, then of feaſting, becauſe that is the end of all men, and the wicked will lay it to his heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For when I ſee a man die, I get this by it, to remember my end alſo, that my day of accompt will come too. When I ſee one die willingly, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts me againſt death, that it is to be embraced rather then ſeared. If I ſee one
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119403:30"/>die reſolutely, it gives me advantage to be valiant alſo, and ſo make the blood of the Martyrs to be the ſeed of the Church. When I ſee one patient in ſickneſſe, and hopefull in death, I gaine ſome confirmation of my aſſurance, that ſurely there is a reward for the righteous, and the patient abiding of the meek ſhall not periſh for ever. For I ſee there is hope laid up in their boſomes, from which Death cannot make them ſtart.</p>
                  <p>And thus the duſt of the dead is like freſh mold caſt into a garden, which makes all things ſpring the better. <hi>Quot juſti, tot miſerationes,</hi> So many good-men, ſo many mercies; if they live, to keep off judgements; if they die, to guide us by examples, that they and we may at laſt meet together in one CHRIST JESUS, who hath left us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, that he may both in life and death be of ſo great power with us, that death may prove a gaine to us, and we a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To whom, together with the Father,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119403:30"/>and the holy Spirit, three Perſons, and one onely true and ever-living Lord God, be rendred, as is moſt due, all honour, and glory, and praiſe, now and for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:31"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Memoriale Sacrum.</hi> AN APPENDIX TO THE Pious and Learned Sermon OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> BENJAMIN SPENCER. <hi>To the perpetuall Memory of the moſt Vertuous Gentlewoman,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> MARY OVERMAN, <hi>Who departed this life, to live with the Saints, on a double Saints day, being that of S.</hi> Philip <hi>and</hi> Jacob. BEING A Speech written, not ſpoken, by her ſorrowfull Husband, THOMAS OVERMAN.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PROV. 10.7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed: but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 112.6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:119403:32"/>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119403:32"/>
                  <head>Memoriale Sacrum.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>To my friends at the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, not at the Sermon.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOu all had, I Confeſſe, (deare friends) upon the ſad occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Invitation, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable Civil Right to this Funerall, not Factious Sermon, falſly ſo chriſtned by ſome ill-meaning men, who would give it no other name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it went to Church, or the Pulpit, but what a factious Conventicle begat, Which it ſeemes has this priviledge (unknowne till now) to miſcall any thing. And ſince Innocence never is in greater danger, then when Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on acts its part againſt it, be pleaſed now to ſee, what would not then be ſuffered in your hearing, this dumbe Sermon ſpeake, both for it ſelfe, and your deceaſed Siſter, a choice young
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119403:33"/>Chriſtian, ſilenced by death. Whoſe bleſſed innocence, hath made her unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſpeaking here, but by a proxie; who being dead, yet ſpeaketh, by her ſurviving husband, her proximated friend, by Gods appointment. Who, as hee muſt not be injurious in the leaſt reſpect, to a deceaſed loving Wife, (that being wholy inconſiſtent, with his laſt dutie to her, to whom he muſt ever owe a pretious memorie) ſo muſt he now publiſh, to the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall world, that ſhe had an unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable right, as dying a Chriſtian, to a peacefull buriall. For, as ſhe lived in faith fixt, ſo ſhe died in the full hope, of a very good Chriſtian. What An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtians then were they that hindred it, I leave for you to judge.</p>
                  <p>I will therefore crave leave to be at this preſent what indeed I am, your ſorrowfull Hiſtorian, yet my hiſtorie muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a ſad glad relation of this our ſiſter, who is now gathered to her heavenly Father. I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt preſented you with the Sermon it ſelfe, which was then ſuppreſt, but not obliterated as you may perceive, you need not feare what Faction ſaith
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119403:33"/>againſt it, here's no ſuch infection. The Sermon you ſhall finde attend the Text, and the occaſion onely, and after take its leave of you. So that all the way, till it bring you home, it will entertaine you with no other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe but the livelie Character of a true Chriſtian, dead to the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. And the example of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed friend will doe no leſſe. A good, and full account ſhe made of that preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time God left her here, which you will plainly perceive, both by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycings ſhe had in her well-ſpent life, and with firme hopes in earneſt of a full aſſurance of a comfortable death. And withall, have her dying example for your living patterne, which will guide you like wiſe, how to make up your accompts well, that you may be happie too, when ere you goe hence, and be no more ſeen; which wee all ſooner or later inevtablie muſt. So that it highly concerns us whilſt wee are here, to make good our accompts firſt, if at laſt wee would not miſſe of that happineſſe of good Chriſtians. And bleſſed be God, that of his fullneſſe, this our deceaſed ſiſter did receive grace
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119403:34"/>for grace; Who driving on towards the marke of her high calling, and aiming at perfection, went on from one degree of grace unto another, till glory came upon her. So that wee doubt not in the leaſt meaſure of her fullneſſe of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whither ſhe is gone.</p>
                  <p>A Progreſſe you ſhall ſee ſhe had, and that in goodnes, being well acquainted with that truely divine maxime, That not to goe forward is to goe backward, and not to thrive in goodnes, not to be good at all. But ſhe ſtood not at ſuch an unhappy ſtay, for I may ſafely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that piety throve with her even from her infancy, humilitie with either, both ſtrove to out-ſtrip each other, neither came to full ſtature, yet perſeverance crowned all. She well knew ſhe muſt carry her goodnes to the grave, if ſhee meant to goe to heaven. For without holynes, no hopes of that happineſſe, to ſee the face of God.</p>
                  <p>Minoritie and Sanctity do not uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meet, yet here both; we ſee a young Woman dead to ſinne, and ready for death, which is no leſſe admirable then rare.</p>
                  <p>A reaſon then you ſee I am ready to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119403:34"/>give you of our good hope wee have of this dead Siſter, twas ſuch indeed, of which wee need not bee aſhamed, no more then ſhe was. So truly lively, that I may confidently ſay, The juſt mans, and the juſt womans hope were here all one. Her end then, muſt needs be like his. I will therefore firſt ſhew you how ſhe led the life of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and next, how ſhee dyed the death of the righteous too. And this taske I ſhall truly performe, if you pleaſe to conſider with me, Firſt, What ſhe did.</p>
                  <p>And in this I muſt beare her witnes, that in all her actions God had her early day, for in them ſhe conſtanſtly looked heaven-ward firſt, and let religion in. Full oft have I been an eye-witnes with joy, of her conſtancie in reading, nay and in writing too, ſome divine tract or other throughout the day, to exerciſe her hand, as well as heart, and both to God-ward, thereby on earth, to traine her ſelfe for heaven. And to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, who have peruſed her pious pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſince her death, both theſe were daily buſied, and piouſly lifted up, her heart in ejaculalory devotions, and her
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119403:35"/>hand in devout tranſcriptions. So that nor here, nor elſe where neither, is any handwriting againſt, but for her. Who was ſo ſincerely conſtant in all her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, that ſhe ſeldome, I may ſay, never, willingly miſſed her dutie to God in prayer either in cloſet, Church, or familie. This was her piety to God. And for the proſecution of the dutie or obedience to her Mother, I have veiwed the deep impreſſions of it long ſince, &amp; to expreſſe it, will give it you, in her Mothers owne phraſe, as neere as I can, as ſhe was heard to utter this ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancous good teſtimony of her: <hi>This dutifull daughter was alwayes won by love, not feare, and that by a motherly admonition onely, but never did I force her to her duty by a ſevere correction.</hi> So that conclude of her we may juſtly from theſe good premiſes, That the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of her nature, made this meek reverence, coupled with love, not feare, in her behaviour to her mother.</p>
                  <p>Give me leave yet farther, to go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſphere of mine owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in her due commendations in ſome other relations. Her love and loyalty to her husband, with whom ſhe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119403:35"/>ran a five yeares race, ſo even, that I may juſtly ſay, we were true yoak fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and good fellowes well met. Our loves were reciprocall, and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſwayd us both, till Death diſſolv'd this Gordian knot, and left me alone to mourne for this loſt Turtle. For though this match on earth, was made in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for her, ſhe reſted unſatisfied, till ſhe reached heaven to obtaine a better, which will admit of no divorce by death: where marryed now ſhe is, to that eternall Bridegroome of her ſoule, Chriſt Jeſus. Stay here with her faine I would, but I muſt leave her to goe on.</p>
                  <p>This Jewell had more Diamonds which did adorne her, other ſpirituall graces which were reſplendent endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in her: I will make them tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent.</p>
                  <p>God had given her that diſcreet pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in her deportment, as that ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly held a reſpective carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her ſuperiours, a friendly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencie towards her equalls, being ever ready to pleaſure all, and loth to offend any. A love ſhe bore to her kindred, both naturall, and adopted,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119403:36"/>and an innate curteſie to all ſhe knew. Beſides, ſhe had Sobriety and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in her ſelfe, and laſtly, Modeſty and Humility in the poſſeſſion of all theſe. All which deſerve our Commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Imitation, and Admiration alſo: Hereby adorning not her ſelfe alone, but ſpreading the pious care of her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in her religious education. And thus you ſee how in all relations, ſhe ran the courſe of her health conſtantly well. So that by this time I hope you are reſolv'd to ſay what you ſee, That ſhe led the life of the righteous, and all good men will be glad thereof.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall now draw on my Speech to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her better end, that you may not doubt but that ſhe dyed the death of the righteous too: And indeed her laſt end was like his, in perfect peace. For having thus wholly dedicated her firſt fruits of ſanctity to God by a pious life, her next ſtudie is to triumph in the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a comfortable death, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring thereby to adjoyne her ſelfe to him, who is become the firſt fruits of them that ſleep: Nothing doubting, but as ſhe was Gods ſervant on earth,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119403:36"/>ſo to be his Saint in heaven. It ſhould ſeeme, ſickneſſe was to this good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man no other then as indeed it is, Deaths elder brother. For, <hi>Omnis paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio</hi> being <hi>Janua lethi,</hi> every paine giving to the ſoule of every Chriſtian, an <hi>Item</hi> of his mortality, ſhe beganne to thinke with her ſelfe, what ſhe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards felt by experience, that her Conſumption might crack her earthen veſſell, and reduce her to her firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. Whereupon ſhee gave that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to ſickneſſe, which ſick <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> gave to <hi>Eſaiah,</hi> ſhe put her houſe in order that ſhee might die, and ſo compoſed her ſelfe wholly in heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditations, the better to prepare her ſoule for heaven, as well as her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for death: Seeming thereby to ſay, <hi>Quo propinquior morti, eo latior:</hi> that the neerer ſhe was to her diſſolution, the firmer ſhe was in her reſolution. <hi>Et vicinior coelo, longior à terrâ:</hi> the neerer ſhe was to heaven, the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her thoughts were from the earth.</p>
                  <p>In her ſickneſſe, being often asked, How ſhe did? ſhe ſtill anſwered, Not ſick, as if then ſhe would thank God
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119403:37"/>for being heart-whole. And having laid one hand on her heart, and lifting up the other heaven-ward, ſaid ſighing, <hi>I am oppreſt; yet thy grace (Lord from above) gives no roome to ſickneſſe.</hi> Each day was to her a new life; and that daily life but one continued ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ever in a Conſumption, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying daily. Yet had God ſo ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied this her tedious viſitation, that ſhe did every day promote her owne good by it; in ſo much that it did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improve, then impaire her: for it did not onely draw her nigher to her end, but to God alſo. So that it ſeemes this fornace did but refine her from her droſſe, and purifie her for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Death came not to her more ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den then expected; not feared, but em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, yea earneſtly deſired. For being conſcious every day, what might befall her ere the next, betaking her ſelfe at laſt wholly to her bed, ſhe doth like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to her continuall prayers. Which ſhe ceaſed not, till her ſelfe ceaſed to be. And having now armed her ſelfe for death, feared no more to goe to her grave, then to her bed, ſince ſhe was certainly aſſured, both tended to her
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119403:37"/>reſt. When ſhee lay downe to ſleepe, ſhe thought it her laſt, knowing then onely ſhe ſhould truly be at reſt, when ſhe ſhould be no more here. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtained the end of her dying pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and of her never dying hopes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus ſet her houſe in order for a more durable repaire, ſweetly compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth her ſelfe for death, and falls aſleep in peace. When ſhe awakes againe, ſhe will account her life not continued, but reſtored, which ſhee was aſcertained ſhould be made good to her at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the juſt. And thus our friend ſleepeth.</p>
                  <p>Now bleſſed be the God of peace, who gave her his peace ſo abundantly both in life and death. For ſhe being one of Chriſts diſciples whilſt ſhe lived, tooke her Maſters legacie hee left his Saints on earth to heaven with her. Where ſhee enjoyes, God the Father of peace, her Redeemer the Prince of peace, his Angels, her fellows, the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of peace, and heaven her inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the place to perfect peace, as well as her. For in the preſence of all theſe muſt needs be the fullneſſe of peace; elſe in a word we know not what it is, nor what ſhe has. Yet this we know of this
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119403:38"/>deare Saint our Siſter, A peace ſhe had internall and externall too, even whilſt ſhe lived here, and they are good fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of that eternall in the heavens. Where to be ſure it concernes them ſhe be at peace, who were the uncivill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of her Funerall Rites, or they might feare thence a ſuddaine requitall for thoſe diſturbances.</p>
                  <p>However: ſuch is the Saints inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable happineſſe, not to be touch'd with things below. And ſuch is hers. Who though ſhe might not be permitted to goe downe to the earth her Mother in peace, no more then ſo me of them, yet can ſhe not be hindred from ſitting downe in peace with thoſe holy ones in the boſome of her Father which is in heaven. It is enough then that God has plac'd her in ſo ſerene a Region, as that ſhe is beyond the ſphere of malice, (though not to envie, yet) to reach her bliſſe, or to moleſt the quiet of her better part. No wonder then this young ſweet Saint haſted thither, whither her early perfections did convey her timely holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being to God moſt acceptable. Yet did ſhe ſtay Gods leaſure here, and went not hence without his great
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119403:38"/>Commiſſion, till patience had her full effect in her, and ſeal'd her up for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: Where now her innocence and patience, have captivated death in perfect tryumph. And this may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us who here remaine behind her, that God in his due time, will ſilence ſuch who ere they be, who thus like foule-mouth'd earth-wormes, not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, faſten thier teeth, <hi>Caniball</hi>-like, upon a dead corps.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>However yet, ſuch times we live to ſee,</l>
                     <l>Depart in peace we may, not buried be.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But God forgive them, (I doe) this unſeaſonable malice to my deareſt ſpouſeſſe, whoſe death gave life to this Funerall Sermon. Yet you will find, as it is in the naturall, ſo in this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all body; this pious Sermon, it could not quicken, except it ſelfe dyed firſt. It did ſo: for it lay ſpeechleſſe, and ſo dead all this while, and now it lyes in thine owne power, by Gods grace aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, to let it quicken both it ſelf and us. Nay, let the power of God accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany this power of godlineſſe, we need not doubt its fruitfulneſſe: but expect
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119403:39"/>rather a very plentifull harveſt, even from thoſe envious men, who pluckt theſe eares too ſoon. So farre were they in practiſe from his precept, who bad them let even the tares grow untill the harveſt. So hope we will, and pray we muſt, that thoſe rude hands who would not let alone a peacefull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, may yet at leaſt reape ſomthing better by it, then the ſhamefull fruits of their inhumanities from it. However, here it is, a Treatiſe I may ſay able to rectify thoſe ſpirits of contention and blind zeale which led them thus to violate the dead, even before they could come into their dormitories. And now they have the Sermon in their eyes, and at their hand when ere they pleaſe to take it. They cannot ſay, but that they have it ready, to convey it to their hearts, one way or other, if God have not deny'd, or they refus'd humility, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it. Elſe I am ſure, it cannot prove to the living a dead letter, but ſerve to quicken them, as well as bury her, which was intended. The preſſe muſt be the Preacher, and as it falls out anticipate the Pulpit. This now, ſupplies that then. A <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119403:39"/>confeſſe no good <hi>decorum</hi> here. Yet let it not trouble thee (good reader) in order unto truth, to ſee it come to light in ſuch diſorder. Let this content thee, Truth hath ſo prevaild, as that it comes at length in greater power. Ready for birth this Sermon was before, yet it has gaind perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by ſtaying in the wombe, and here that preſſeth forth in greater ſtrength which was ſuppreſt by ſome miſtaking men, even at the Pulpit. Yet this muſt I ſay, had we had the happineſſe to have heard it from the Authors lips, wee had met with <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> lively voice, and golden mouth, in the delivery, which would have mov'd us more, yet writing teacheth more. This giveth thee leaſure for thy contemplation, and leave thou haſt to bore thine eare and tanſack thine owne heart when ere thou wilt. Words ſpoken, have their wings, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo eloquently or aptlie ſpoken. And though like apples of gold in pictures of Silver, they doe too neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſemble thoſe apples of Sodome which turne to nothing with a touch,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119403:40"/>and doe too often teach but for one houre: But hee that writeth ſeemes to teach for ever. By voice we profit thoſe in compaſſe onely; by penne, thoſe at the greateſt diſtance, yea the yet unborne. Which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration moved me with ſo much zeale, though little skill, to penne this Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Oration, in honour of my moſt beloved Spouſe, who though dead, juſtly beſpake this bleſſed memory of her ſelfe in the ſad heart of her ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Husband, who hath no better Trophee to erect, worthy ſo much vertue.</p>
                  <p>And if in this laſt duty to my deareſt, I ſeeme a paſſionate admirer of her, I have reaſon to appeare ſo; And you muſt pardon me to take my leave with ſome ſolemnity of that ſame houſe wherein did lately dwell that ſoule, which was indeed the ſoule of my contentment. And you may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive none elſe knew how to value this jewell ſo well as did the owner: who muſt acknowledge it no low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd happineſſe to have enjoyed the ſociety of ſo ſweet a companion. Yet if you thinke I glory too much in this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119403:40"/>particular, I muſt tell you, as concerning my ſelfe, I doe not glory, but in the Croſſe of Chriſt, who was pleaſed to take from me this crowne of my rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing upon earth. But I muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my ſelfe, and not dwell too long in this kind of ſpeech. Onely thus I leave her, the joy of my life is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and I muſt be patient till I can follow after.</p>
                  <p>You all ſee by this time, That as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did with honey, ſo have I all this while done with my ſpeech of this bleſſed woman, imparted ſome of her ſpirituall endowments, that you alſo might have a taſte of her heavenly conſolations.</p>
                  <p>And now to you, my loving friends, will I addreſſe my ſpeech: Yet firſt, preſent you with the Sermon: Ye had had it ſooner, had the learned Author enjoy'd his wonted health, to have tranſcrib'd a Copie. It is now at laſt in your poſſeſſion, you have had it long enough in expectation, and you deſerve it now. You travelled for it firſt, ſince thirſted for it, and now at laſt tis come home to you, to make amends for your loſt journey then. I cannot be ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119403:41"/>to the dead, nor yet ſo injurious to the living, as to defraud either of their due. Nor ſhall it ere be ſaid, I engroſſed that to my ſelfe, which did ſo truly belong unto you all. You all did honour me (I thank you) to follow the body of my deare Bed-fellow with ſolemnity to her bed of reſt; But ſee what happened, (to my grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter griefe I ſpeake it, for it added much to my affliction then) you were diſmiſt without your ſpirituall banquet. Unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill men diſpoyled you of your Feaſt, and having faſted from it ever ſince, you needs muſt have it now: And here it is. Fall to it when you pleaſe. I doe perſwade my ſelfe, you came ſo well reſolved, as that you meant to profit by the dead, why ſhould I fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate this chiefe end of yours? I need not, others did, who promiſed well, but ill performd it. They ſpake of peace, yet would not let it follow her to the grave.</p>
                  <p>If to excuſe themſelves, they aske, What profit is a Sermon to the dead?</p>
                  <p>I muſt anſwer, it is the buſineſſe of the living, who were by them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded of this excellent Sermon:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119403:41"/>wherein the Prophet <hi>Ezechiels</hi> dead and dry bones are gathered together to a happy Reſurrection, Death it ſelfe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened by the pious Authors eloquence, into a profitable life: By whoſe skilfull guidance thou mayſt be inſtructed ſo to live, that thou ſhalt never dye; and ſo to dye, that thou ſhalt live for ever. What kind of Adders then were thoſe, who did not onely ſtoppe their owne, but others eares, againſt the voyce of this wiſe Charmer here? Who, how injuriouſly he was accuſed, upon ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion for this Sermon, has by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of it, made you judges, and the world beſides.</p>
                  <p>And now high time it is to cloze with you, (deare Mother) and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move my foot a little from this houſe of ſorrow, at leaſt from the depth of it, to comfort you. And you will give me leave to ſay after the ſtory of ſo much goodneſſe eminent in our depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed friend, wee have ſomething to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in, in the midſt of all our teares, that ſhe both lived and dyed ſo exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarily well.</p>
                  <p>It hath pleaſed God indeed, to call you and me in a more eſpeciall manner
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119403:42"/>to the houſe of mourning. A ſad truth, if wee conſult with fleſh and blood onely. God hath of late depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us of a very neere relation to each of us; You, of an obedient daughter in her youth; Me, of a boſome friend too ſoone. Both theſe were deare rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in our affections, which having had a <hi>Benjamins</hi> portion in our love, muſt needs have the ſame proportion in our ſorrow for her loſſe. I can no more forget my wife, then you your daughter. I muſt acknowledge, the ſeparation of an obedient daughter from an indulgent mother, to be cauſe ſufficient of lamentation: yet you will pardon me if I ſay that I have more. If you conſider us in thoſe ſacred bonds wherein heaven had joyned us, where I met with ſo much mutuall converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and affection, with ſuch an union, that as living I could not over-love, ſo neither now over-grieve the ſeparation. The tribute of my teares muſt needs be larger then, who beare a larger ſhare in the ſame loſſe.</p>
                  <p>But we will not vie teares in this ſad contention, but rather ſtrive to beare our ſelves as Chriſtian Mourners,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119403:42"/>Not ſo full of teares, as hope. She dyed in hope, let us mourne too, as for our Freind who is but gone before to that place of joy, whither we hope, to follow her in Gods due time. Hee onely make us ready as ſhe was, and then wee ſhall not need to feare our Maſters call, how ſoone or late, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. So ſhall not death over-maſter us, but we ſhall conquer it, through him that tooke away its hurtfull ſting. And let us now remember, all teares are wiped from her eyes, why ſhould ours then, ſtand full of teares for her? If all her ſorrowes be fallen aſleepe and buried in the grave, Why ſhould ours live too paſſionatly to bemoane her? Let us not then drop a teare more here, but rather lend each other both our hands to helpe us beare this weighty croſſe betweene us. I muſt confeſſe, no croſſes doe ſo much affect us as thoſe which teare away the things wee dearlieſt love, and when the cheife object of our affections is taken from us, a generall lamentation followes it through all the powers both of ſoule and body. We cannot ſuffer it to be divided from us without
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119403:43"/>abundance of teares. I neede not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie it.</p>
                  <p>Yet muſt I give my Soule this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation for the loſſe, (If I doe not ſo miſcall the bleſſed death) of my deare Spouſe, ſhe is not dead, but ſleepeth, And if no more. I may thinke further, Worldly occaſions have many nights ſeparated our bodies, when the next morning has rejoyned us; and it is but one night, one ſhort night of this dull life ſhe ſhall be from me, when the morning of glory ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, wee ſhall appear together. And ſince this comfort of my life could not here ſtay with me, this comfort is my ſtay of life, that a little time of patience will bring mee to her.</p>
                  <p>And for you (deare Mother) the Argument is as good: you may mourn exceſſively, as <hi>David</hi> did for <hi>Abſalom;</hi> Yet you muſt expect a <hi>loab</hi> to chide you for it. So much the more, in that <hi>David</hi> had more cauſe to bewaile his <hi>Abſolom,</hi> then you, your <hi>Mary,</hi> hee knew not how God would deale with that rebellious Sonne, but you cannot doubt but he has dealt well with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119403:43"/>your obedient daughter.</p>
                  <p>My advice therefore to you, ſhall be no other then this in briefe, neither too much to remember, nor altogether to forget ſo good a daughter. Could ſhe not have dyed, it had been worthy of wonder, not at all that ſhe is dead.</p>
                  <p>I might ſave you, and my ſelfe this <hi>quere,</hi> Whether we loved her, whom we lately have forgone? and could we love her, and not wiſh her happie? Could ſhe be happie, and not die? God gave you this daughter as a gift, and me this wife, and hee hath againe taken her as his due, may hee not doe with his <hi>Theodoſia,</hi> his owne gift, as hee pleaſes? It was <hi>Iobs</hi> ſaying in the midſt of all his loſſes, <hi>The Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, and the Lord taketh away, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In all afflictions, we muſt conſider, both what we have loſt, and what we have left, and bleſſe God in every loſſe that we have loſt no more, having ſo many things to be deprived of.</p>
                  <p>Tis ſome comfort in calamity not to be altogether miſerable. And it is as much as we can expect whilſt we are here, to part with our earthly happineſſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119403:44"/>by degrees, tis but a kindlie paſſage to thoſe eternall ones above: which will ſufficiently recompence all our loſſes here below.</p>
                  <p>This muſt be the conſideration which in this, and the like occaſions muſt ſatisfy both you and me.</p>
                  <p>For any other ſatisfaction, we muſt not expect. Nor muſt the deniall of that Chriſtian ſolemnity, which was deſigned for her more honourable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment afflict or trouble us, we know the times, and men. And if we looke abroad, we ſhall behold great, noble, farnous perſons, thruſt into their graves with leſſer ceremony. And we muſt not thinke much to ſympathize a little with the diſquiet of the times.</p>
                  <p>And if yet any be ſo cenſorious, to look upon this ſpeech, or that Sermon with an ill aſpect, in reſpect that it is now made publicke; It ſuffices me that I have hereby given my cheife freinds their owne content, which is my duty. For ſure I am, they were ſufficiently diſcontented with what befell at the Funerall. And I have hereby decently interred my deare Wife, (having no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way left me to performe it) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119403:44"/>the laſt duty of an affectionate Husband. For till now, ſhe was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in ſilence, whom no man can blame me if I perpetually ſpeake of, as well as continually remember. And I muſt further profeſſe, that both the Preacher, and my ſelfe, have modeſtly and truly deciphered her proper Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, as became her by the law of Chriſtianity to be reported of.</p>
                  <p>If now all this vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe make thee (whoever thou art that readeſt) preſſe forward to the ſame practiſe, Thou wilt ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently juſtifie the juſtneſſe of this true, though ceremonious commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
                  <p>And you my freinds, as you will acknowledge, that I have thus but paid the honour I owed to her beloved aſhes: So you will confeſſe your ſelves honoured, by the intereſts and relations you once had, to ſo deſerving a Saint; And for her ſake, retaine with love, the antient reſpects and freindſhip, to her, lately beloved Husband, and ſtill, your freind, and Servant,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>THO: OVERMAN.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
